Guide to the Anderson family Papers, 1848-1963
Department of Special Collections
Anderson family Papers,
1848-1963
Anderson family
32 linear ft (ca. 45,000 items).
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Family of Scottish-English origins which came to the United States in the middle of the nineteenth century. The family settled on the East Coast, later moving West; the Andersons contributed to society in the fields of theology, education and literature. Melville Best Anderson was an author, translator and teacher whose particular interest was the work of Dante. From 1891-1910, he taught in the English Department at Stanford University, serving as first chairman of the department.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Mrs. Robert Van Vleck Anderson (Gracella Rountree), 1963, Patricia Sage Liedtke, 1987, and Catharine Brinton Cary, 1997.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Robert Van Vleck Anderson (Gracella Rountree), 1963, Patricia Sage Liedtke, 1987, and Catharine Brinton Cary, 1997.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Anderson family.; Anderson, Edward Coffin, 1821-1890.; Anderson, Edward Playfair, 1856-1951.; Anderson, Gracella Rountree.; Anderson, Malcolm Playfair, 1878-1919.; Anderson, Melville Best, 1851-1933.; Anderson, Robert Van Vleck, 1884-1949,.; Browne, Francis Fisher, 1843-1913.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931.; McClure, Samuel S.; Kellogg, Vernon.; Stanford, Jane Lathrop, 1828-1905.; Phillips, John S., 1883-1920.; Muir, John, 1838-1914.; Toynbee, Paget Jackson, 1855-1932.; Walling, Anna Strunsky.; Wilbur, Ray Lyman, 1875-1949.; Willis, Bailey, 1857-1949.; Reinhardt, Aurelia Henry, 1877-1948.; Finley, John H.; Lummis, Charles Fletcher, 1859-1928.; Griggs, Edward Howard.; Hoover, Lou Henry.; Branner, John Casper, 1850-1922.; Breasted, James Henry, 1865-1935.; Hall, Howard J.; Flèugel, Ewald, 1863-1914.; Mirrielees, Edith R.; Ross, Edward Alsworth, 1866-1951.; The Dial.$ga monthly review and index of current literature.; McClure's magazine.; American literature--20th century.; Duke of Bedford Expedition, 1904.; Women.; Manuscripts (for publication).; Photoprints.
Scope and Content Note
THE ANDERSON FAMILY PAPERS cover the history, activities, lives, interests and accomplishments of three generations of an unusual American family.
The collection contains letters, of both personal and business nature, manuscripts of the literary and scientific work done by members of the family, photographs, snapshots, official documents (passports, certifications, deeds, wills, insurance papers, naturalization papers, death certificates, marriage certificates, etc.) and clippings concerning the political and historical matters of the day, and personal activities of the family.
Also contained in the collection are a number of genealogical notes. These notes show the family to have come chiefly of English-Scottish origins on one side and, in one branch, of Hudson River Duton on the other. They seem to have been of sturdy, middle-class stock, neither very rich nor very poor, essentially religious, Protestant, thrifty and, for the most part, well educated. There were ministers, lawyers and teachers in the family; one member was president of several colleges. In one generation there were two excellent scientists. There were writers, and several members were rewarded for service in the Union Army. Others were farmers, merchants, sea-faring men and fishermen.
The first member of the family, for whom a fairly complete record is available, is Edward Coffin Anderson. The collection contains his letters, records and certifications. From these documents can be gathared quite a complete history of his career as a minister, college teacher and college president as well as the history of his own personal life and the childhood background of Melville Rest Anderson.
The central figure of the collection if Melville Bost Anderson, first son of Edward Coffin Anderson. The correspondence of Melville Anderson, with his parents, during his college years at Cornell University gives a good picture of the lives of the family at this particular time.
After his student years, both in the United States and in Europe, he began his long literary life. He contributed to various literary publications, the most notable of which was THE DIAL. Through his contributions to THE DIAL, he became a friend of Francis Fisher Browne, the Editor, and this long and satisfying friendship can be traced through the Browne letters contained in the collection.
The Browne letters are of special interest for in then can be seen the very high regard that Browne had for Anderson as one literary man for another, as well as the close personal friendship between the two men. There letters also contain a great deal of business matter concerning literary interests of the day.
Other letters of particular interest were written to Melville best Anderson by Samuel S. McClure (editor of McClure's Magazine), John Muir, Anna Strunsky Walling, Gordon Craig, John Vance Cheney, Howard Criggs and Paget Toynbee. Most of this correspondence relates to business matters, but it also contains much to show the strong personal regard for Professor Anderson.
Most of Melville best Anderson's correspondence consists of letters to him rather than from him. These letters indicate that he had a strong gift of friendship, not only for his contemporaries and colleagues, but for his students as well. Samuel S. McClure had been a student under Anderson as had Anna Strunsky Walling and John H. Finley, who was for many years connected with the New York Times and was president of City College of New York. The student for whom he had the greatest affection was Agnes Smith Mannucci-Capponi.
The collection also contains Melville Best Anderson's manuscripts of his work on Dante which was the greatest interest of his literary life. There are manuscripts of his other publications and his teaching notes.
THE ANDERSON PAPERS also contain the manuscripts, photographs, letters and clippings of Melville Best Anderson's two sons, Malcolm Playfair Anderson and Robert vanVleck Anderson. Malcolm Anderson was a [zoologist] 1/31/77 and natural scientist, interested chiefly in the Orient. He left not only his scientific notes, but also notes for a few short stories concerning the lives of the people where he had lived and worked in China. Robert Anderson, a geologist, was interested primarily in oil and was for some years in North Africa. Here he was interested not only in oil but in the archeology of the region. His correspondence with the United States Geological Survey and with James H. Breasted of the oriental Institute gives some idea of the importance of his discoveries.
The women of the Anderson family should not be overlooked. They seem to have been as sturdy a group as their husbands. Their letters are interesting not only as personal documents but as reflections of the age, showing the great change in the status of women over four generations. They were not career women; they were essentially housewives and mothers of families, but their lives were active, and from their letters it is evident that they were educated, quick minded and interested in many things outside the usual domestic routine.
Biographical Note
THE ANDERSON FAMILY PAPERS cover the history of a distinguished family that, up to a point, followed a somewhat typical pattern in America. Of Scottish-English origins, with a short history in the Maritime Provinces, Canada, the family came to the United States in the middle of the nineteenth century. They settled on the East coast, later moving West. Here the Andersons diverged from the usual pattern. They made major contributions to society in the fields of theology, education and literature. They were intellectual people rather than industrialists. They did not lay railroads or pan for gold or wage wars with the Indians on the frontier. They did, however, found schools, preach sermons, write books and make substantial scholarly and scientific contributions to the community.
Edward Coffin Anderson, the first member of the family for whom there are extensive records, was born on Prince Edward Island, Maritime Provinces, Canada, in 1821, the fourth of thirteen children. His grandfather, John Anderson, had migrated to North America from Scotland with his brother, David, and son, David. David Anderson, the son, married Miss Jeanette Coffin, whose father had come to Prince Edward Island from Nantucket. Edward Coffin Anderson received his education in Nova Scotia at Acadia College, and later went to Newton Seminary near Boston for further theological study. While he was attending Acadia College at Wolfville, Nova Scotia, he met Miss Helen Best, a teacher in a school for girls.
The Best Family was also of Scottish descent. Helen's mother, Isabella Playfair, was a daughter of Robert Lawyer Playfair and a niece of John Playfair, the great mathematician of the University of Edinburgh. Her mother, Margaret McNevin was said to have been a brilliant and clever woman. When John Playfair was contemplating marriage, a friend advised, If you marry Margaret McNevin, all your children will be gifted. Isabella was educated at a school for young ladies conducted by her two aunts in Edinburgh. At sixteen she married Henry Best, of the British Navy, and they settled in Nova Scotia. They had thirteen children. Later, to help out the family finances, she established a school for girls in Wolfville, Nova Scotia. Isabella, herself, served as headmistress and two of her daughters, including Helen Best, were teachers in the school.
In 1850, Helen Best became the wife of Edward Coffin Anderson and later that same year the young couple emigrated to the United States where they lived for the rest of their lives. Anderson, when he finished his training at Newton Seminary, was ordained in the Baptist Church and began his long career of preaching and teaching. His first appointment was at Kalamazoo, Michigan. Edward and Helen Anderson had three sons, Melville Best Anderson, Robert Playfair Anderson (who died in infancy), and Edward Playfair Anderson.
From Kalamazoo, the family went to Newton Center, Massachusetts, to Milford, New Hampshire, and back to Kalamazoo where Mr. Anderson was professor of Classical Languages and acting president of Kalamazoo Baptist College. From Kalamazoo, they went to Margett, Michigan where Anderson was pastor. In 1866, the Andersons went to Portland, Oregon where Anderson assumed the post of pastor of the Baptist Church, and from there he went to San Jose, California. After a short time in San Jose, the family returned to the East coast, to Groveland, Massachusetts, where Mr. Anderson was pastor and also principal of Highlands Academy in Petersburg, Massachusetts. He became president of Ottowa College in Ottawa, Kansas, and pastor of Lake City Baptist Church in Lake City, Minnesota. About 1880, he became president of McMinnville College, McMinnville, Oregon, a post he held for seven years. In 1887, he had a stroke, and died three years later, in 1890, at the home of his son, Edward Playfair Anderson, in Lansing, Michigan.
From this varied background comes the central figure in the ANDERSON FAMILY PAPERS collection, Melville Best Anderson. The first son of Edward Coffin and Helen Best Anderson, he was born in Kalamazoo, Michigan in 1851. He attended Cornell University where, to a great extent, he worked his own way. The Papers indicate that he was an excellent student. At Cornell, he met David Starr Jordan and began a friendship that lasted for more than fifty years, and later brought Anderson to Stanford. In 1872, he graduated from Cornell and for several years he taught in the secondary schools in Appleton, Wisconsin. Jordan was also teaching there at the time.
In 1875, Melville Anderson married Miss Charlena van Vleck. Miss van Vleck, a student at Lawrence College, and her mother, Mrs. Louisa Gurnee van Vleck, widow of a Union soldier, had a home in Appleton. The van Vleck family came from the Hudson River country and were of Dutch descent. Charlena's mother was also from the Hudson Valley, but of English stock.
In 1875, Melville Anderson went to Gottingen, Germany and then to the University of Paris. In 1877, he returned to the United States and began his literary and professorial career. He went first to Butler University where he was awarded an M. A. degree and became professor of Modern Languages. Three years later, 1880, he went to Knox College where he remained for six years. After leaving, Knox, Melville Anderson spent a year at Purdue University and in 1887 he went to the State University of Iowa. During these years, he was writing and translating as well as teaching.
In October of 1891, he came to the newly established Leland Stanford Junior University, at the invitation of its president, David Starr Jordan. Anderson became the first chairman of the English Department, and it was at Stanford that he did the greater part of his teaching and writing. He taught from 1891 until 1910, retiring somewhat earlier than the usual age. A Carnegie grant enabled him to live in Italy where he continued his studies of Dante, the great work of his literary life. During this time, Mrs. Anderson and the two sons remained at home. Melville Anderson returned to California, but never lived permanently at Stanford. He went to LaJolla to be near his brother Edward, and died there in 1933.
Edward Playfair Anderson, second son of Edward Coffin and Helen Best Anderson, was born in 1856 and also pursued a teaching career. He received his A. B. degree from the University of Michigan in 1879 and his PhD. in 1886. He studied in France in 1880 and was professor of Latin and French at McMinnville College for two years, 1882-84. He returned to the University of Michigan to work on his doctorate. In 1888 he resumed teaching, first at Ohio University, then at Michigan Agricultural College and at Miami University in Ohio. Edward married Miss Hattie Amelia Baker and they had eight children. He moved to LaJolla, California where he died in 1951.
Melville Best Anderson had two sons who lived to maturity. Malcolm Playfair Anderson, born in 1878, was from his earliest boyhood interested in natural science and natural history. He graduated from Stanford as a zoologist. After graduation, his work and interests took him to many parts of Asia, chiefly China, Korea and Japan. In 1904, he lead the Duke of Bedford Expedition to the Orient, collecting mammals for the British Museum. He took many photographs and made full notes on the collections. Also, he left notes on several short stories which dealt with the lives of the people with whom he lived and worked in the Orient.
Malcolm married Miss Elizabeth Gurnee, a distant cousin, and they had one son who died in infancy. In 1919 Malcolm Anderson was killed in an accident in the shipyards at Oakland, California. His death cut short a promising career as a naturalist and explorer.
The youngest of Melville Best Anderson's sons, Robert van Vleck Anderson, was born in 1884 and like all the Anderson children, received the early part of his education in Germany. Robert Anderson attended Stanford, graduating as a geologist. He also was interested in natural history and archeology. He was in Asia for a time with his brother, Malcolm, and then went to North Africa as an oil geologist.
In North Africa, he discovered some hitherto unexplored prehistoric caves. He was fully aware of the importance of this discovery and, with grants from the United States Geological Survey and with help and encouragement from the Oriental Institute and James H. Breasted, he was able to excavate them.
In 1923, he married Miss Gracella Rountree of Berkeley, California. They had three children. The Andersons lived in North Africa for many years and traveled widely in Europe, Asia and South America. He worked in Washington, D. C. with the United States Geological Survey from 1906-1913. After that time he worked for several oil companies, including Whitehall Petroluem in London, one of two British firms, and as a consultant to many others in various parts of the world. Upon his retirement in 1945, he lived near Stanford-company whitehall Petroleum in London where he was a research associate until his death in 1949. His widow, children and grandchildren are still (1963) living in the vicinity.
DESCRIPTION OF SERIES
- Melville Best Anderson Letters to parents, wife, brother and children. Also biographical note and outline of letters by Gracella R. Anderson. (Box 1 - 5)
- Correspondence of Charlena vanVleck Anderson. Letters to Melville Best Anderson, mother, children, brother, friends. Letters from friends. Diaries. (Box 6 - 7)
- Letters to Melville Best Anderson. Summary and Addenda (Box 8 - 20)
- Journals, account books, note books, diaries by Melville Best Anderson (Box 21)
- Poetry, miscellaneous manuscripts, letters by Melville Best Anderson. Publications (Box 22)
- Dante Manuscript (Box 23)
- Honorary Degree from the University of Aberdeen. Miscellaneous reviews, etc. Obituary Notices. (Box 24)
- Lecture Notes (Box 25 - 26)
- Lecture Notes. Official Papers (Box 27)
- Edward Coffin Anderson (fa ther of Melville Best Anderson) and Helen Best Anderson Letters and Official papers (Box 28 - 32)
- Charlena vanVleck Anderson Official paper s, Letters to sons. (Box 33)
- vanVleck Family. Letters, records, Official papers (Box 34)
- Louisa Gurnee vanVleck (mother of Charlena vanVleck Anderson) Letters (Box 35)
- Miscellaneous Letters (Box 36)
- Gurnee Family, Letters. Edward Playfair Anderson (brother of Melville Best Anderson) Letters (Box 37)
- Edward Playfair Anderson and wife, Hattie Baker Anderson. Letters (Box 38)
- Genealogical Notes. Anderson Family, vanVleck Family, Gurnee Family, Playfair Family, Best Family (Box 39)
- Malcolm Playfair Anderson, Son of Melville Best Anderson. Note books, letters, Manuscripts, publications, photographic prints and negatives. Maps. (Box 40 - 44)
- Robert vanVleck Anderson. Letters, official papers, publications, etc. (Box 45 - 58)
- Photographs and snap shots. (Box 59 - 61)
  SEE ADDENDA FOR ADDITIONAL PHOTOGRAPHS, GLASS SLIDES & LOCATION OF MAPS.
Container List
- Biographical Notes 1870 - 1890Melville Best Anderson (Box 1, Folder 1-21)
- Outline of Letters by Gracella Rountree Anderson Letters of Melville Best Anderson Childhood - 1875
- Melville Best Anderson Letters Early Letters - 1873
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1873 - 1875
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1876 - 1883
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1884 - 1889
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1890 - 1895To his mother, Helen Best Anderson (Box 2, Folder 1-21)
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1896 - 1904To his mother, Helen Best Anderson
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1875 - 1880to Charlena vanVleck Anderson
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1881 - 1882to Charlena vanVleck Anderson
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1885 - 1891to Charlena vanVleck Anderson (Box 3, Folder 1-18)
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1892 - 1895to Charlena vanVleck Anderson
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1896 - 1904to Charlena vanVleck Anderson
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1905 - 1910to Charlena vanVleck Anderson (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1911 - 1915to Charlena vanVleck Anderson (Box 4, Folder 4-10)
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1916 - 1923to Charlena vanVleck Anderson
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1881 - 1896to Louisa vanVleck, mother-in-law (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1876 - 1896to Balfour vanVleck, brother-in-law (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1890 - 1915to son, Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 4, Folder 13-15)
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1871 - 1900to brother Edward Playfair Anderson (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1890 - 1895to son Balfour Anderson (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1890 - 1891to daughter Gertrude Anderson (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Gertrude Anderson Letters 1890 - 1891to father Melville Best Anderson and to Grandmother, Helen Best Anderson (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Balfour Anderson Letters 1890 - 1894to father Melville Best Anderson, to grandmother Helen Best Anderson and to Elizabeth Gurnee, cousin (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Melville Best Anderson, Letters 1890 - 1896to son Robert vanVleck Anderson (Box 4, Folder 21-22, Box 5, Folder 1-21)
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1906 - 1910to son Robert vanVleck Anderson
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1911 - 1913to son Robert vanVleck Anderson
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1914 - 1917to son Robert vanVleck Anderson (Box 6)
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1918 - 1920to son Robert vanVleck Anderson (Box 6, Folder 29)
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1921 - 1922to son Robert vanVleck Anderson (Box 6, Folder 30)
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1923 - 1924to son Robert vanVleck Anderson (Box 6, Folder 31)
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1925 - 1926to son Robert vanVleck Anderson (Box 7, Folder 32)
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1927 - 1929to son Robert van Vleck Anderson (Box 7, Folder 33)
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1930 - 1931to son Robert vanVleck Anderson (Box 7, Folder 34)
- Melville Best Anderson Letters 1931 - 1933to son Robert vanVleck Anderson (Box 7, Folder 35)
- Melville Best Anderson to Alice Hays 1933 (Box 7, Folder 35a)
- Charlena van Vleck Anderson Letters 1876 - 1882to Melville Best Anderson (Box 8, Folder 36)
- Charlena van Vleck Anderson Letters 1885 - 1891to Melville Best Anderson (Box 8, Folder 37)
- Charlena van Vleck Anderson Letters 1892 - 1905to Melville Best Anderson (Box 8, Folder 38)
- Charlena van Vleck Anderson Letters 1906 - 1923to Melville Best Anderson (Box 8, Folder 39)
- Charlena van Vleck Anderson Letters 1875 - 1876to mother Louisa van Vleck (Box 8, Folder 40)
- Charlena van Vleck Anderson Letters 1877 - 1896to mother Louisa van Vleck (Box 8, Folder 41)
- Charlena van Vleck Anderson Diaries 1875 and 1876 (Box 8, Folder 42)
- Letters to Charlena van Vleck Anderson from Classmates and friends, 1865until about the time of her marriage. (Box 9, Folder 43)
- Letters to Charlena van Vleck Anderson from friends (several letters from Mrs. Leland Stanford) 1877 - 1883 (Box 9, Folder 44)
- Letters to Charlena van Vleck Anderson from friends, about 1890. Many undated. (Box 9, Folder 45)
- Letters to Charlena van Vleck Anderson from German friends. (Box 9, Folder 46)
- Letters to Charlena van Vleck Anderson. Letters from Helena 1875 - 1877 (Box 9, Folder 47)
- Letters to Charlena van Vleck Anderson from the family (Box 9, Folder 48)
- Letters of Charlena van Vleck Anderson to brother Balfour van Vleck 1876 (Box 9, Folder 49)
- Letters of Helen Best Anderson to Louisa van Vleck, 1875 - 1895 (Box 9, Folder 50)
- Letters of Henry K. Metcalf to Louisa van Vleck, Charlena van Vleck, Balfour van Vleck and Melville Best Anderson 1869 - 1891 (Box 9, Folder 51)
- Letters to Charlena van Vleck Anderson 1876 - 1878from Auguste J. C. Beach, Gottengen, Germany. (Box 9, Folder 52)
- Summary (index) of Letters to Melville Best Anderson (Box 9, Folder 53)
- Letters to Melville Best Anderson General Correspondence A - Ayer (Box 9, Folder 54)
- Letters to Melville Best Anderson from John Caspar Branner (Box 10, Folder 55)
- Letters to Melville Best Anderson General Correspondence Bade - Bender (Box 10, Folder 56)
- Letters to Melville Best Anderson General Correspondence Berger - Bradley (Box 10, Folder 57)
- Letters to Melville Best Anderson General Correspondence, Bradshaw - Butler (Box 10, Folder 58)
- THE DIAL Correspondence, 1886 (Box 11, Folder 59)
- THE DIAL Correspondence, 1887 - 1888 (Box 11, Folder 60)
- THE DIAL Correspondence, 1889 (Box 11, Folder 61)